Is that you dialed in on the phone there, Leigh Ann?
Yes.
>> Okay. I thought I recognized that phone number.
And I show 7 so I'd like to call the public hearing to order.
So the public hearing is to solicit comment on the application of 50 seven Hendy Road
LLC to deposit, fill and construct a single family home in a flood zone in accordance with section ten
point four point nine of the town's zoning regulations.
The public hearing was continued until today at the request of the applicant to consider alternatives and options brought up during the public hearing.
The hearing is not about being able to build in a flood prone zone that has already been asked and answered by the zoning board of appeals.
The session is being video recorded as the conversations from this hearing will become part of the public record.
I'll start by asking the applicants or their engineer or attorney to discuss the application in particular determination
of width as it pertains to the Andover zoning regulations.
Then
>> I'll ask agent Halsey to provide input on the applications and in particular compliance with Andover's
zoning regulations.
Then
>> the commission members will have the opportunity to ask questions
During the public hearing, all Commission members
will have the opportunity to ask questions and provide input.
During deliberations following the hearing, only seated members of the Commission will be able to provide input.
And during that,
I do expect to
see
Kevin
in place of
Susan England who let me know she would not be here tonight.
Any members of the public will have the opportunity to provide comments or questions. I'd ask members of the public to state their name for the record to assist in preparing the minutes from the hearing.
>> Good evening, folks. My name is Alan Parkington.
I live
at
56 Hendy Road directly across the street from the proposed lot.
>> Okay.
Yep, we're not ready to start taking input yet.
We'll get there.
The pending application section has the town's website that has several documents associated with the application.
We can call up any of those that we need to.
And but we won't necessarily display all the documents
that make up the public record
unless
desired.
So any questions before we begin this evening?
Hearing none,
I offer
the applicants
the opportunity
to
share with the Commission what
they have
decided on as far as the various options we discussed at the last public hearing and
go from there.
Chairperson, can you hear us? I can hear you. Yep. Okay. Thank you.
>> So we wanted to thank you guys again for continuing this proceeding and allowing us additional time to consider our application.
There were a few options, as Jed mentioned, that were ways to proceed and better meet the zoning regulations for the town.
Our engineer Andrew has taken into consideration the general information provided by attorney brands at the last meeting.
We now understand the regulations for the building setback line to mean at least 50 feet from the center of the traveled way. As you can see on the revised plan we provided,
we show the 50 foot line for a point of reference and the new setback line at 93 feet.
This actually worked out really well to be in compliance on all areas of the regulations,
even with the unusual shape of this lot.
We were able to obtain the 200 foot lot width required touching but in front of the building line
and keeping it parallel to Hendy Road as requested.
We sincerely appreciate the time and consideration from all who generously offered suggestions at the last meeting, and we're hopeful that we're showing we're doing everything we can to meet or exceed every regulation in a pursuit of building a home for my family.
Our engineer Andrew Bushnell is available to answer any questions you might have. And again, we thank you guys for some more of your time tonight.
>> Okay,
thank you.
And agent Halsey,
would you like to comment on the application?
>> I have really no further comments.
I mean, the only outstanding issue,
as far as
I recall was the
interpretation
of the lot with definition.
And
there seems to be perhaps,
it's been suggested that it means
exactly 50 or a minimum 50.
In my understanding, that was
think Attorney Brantz, I don't know whether he's on the
call or not. MR. He is.
I would refer to him on his
interpretation
of that.
>> MR. Well,
as I recall
from the discussion, and I did go back and look at
the record,
attorney branch made the comment that some towns
have their ordinance specify at least 50 feet.
If we look at
our
regulation,
it doesn't say at least 50 feet. It says 50 feet.
And so
I guess that
is still the rub.
And in fact,
if you look at
there's some further words after that that say
if you don't have
the 200
feet of width
at the building line,
what you do have
is a rear lot.
And if you look at the definition in our regulations of a rear lot,
that's
exactly what we're looking at, where you don't have the 200
foot width
at
the 50 foot from the center line of the road.
So while some towns
that might
meet the definition
if their wording said at least 50 feet,
we can call up our definition
again here, but
it does in fact
say
50 feet.
So from my conclusion,
what we have is a rear lot
and not a lot that complies with 200 foot width
for a lot other than a rear lot.
And so I know we did
provide several other options
at the last meeting.
And those ranged anywhere from leaving the lot lines as they currently exist
to buying the town property,
to requesting a variance,
or to treat the lot as you would like to make it as a rear lot.
Or you
could possibly put in an easement.
And since
all the property is owned by a single owner, it should be
fairly easy to,
in my mind, comply with a few of those other options
considering that we don't
meet
and we can take it to a vote. I'm only one vote.
But the way I read the regulations
would be that we don't meet the 50 feet there.
Attorney branch would you care to provide anything.
>> In addition to that. Yes Mr. Chairman, for the record Mark Brantz.
I
saw the email
to
Mr. Hallisey
from Mr. Bushnell
quoting me as saying at the last meeting that the commission that the language was at least 50 feet.
I
was pretty confident I did not say that.
I went back I watched the meeting again.
I know Jim Halsey did also I believe you did also Mr. Chairman
that is not what I said I
guess I'm feeling irritated because this is the second time in the course of this application where I've been quoted
to the commission without my knowledge without being cc'd
and incorrectly.
I
said that sometimes
say at least 50 feet that I thought the commission could construe it that way if they wish to
but I did not say that that was my recommendation or that that was how it should be read I felt the Commission had flexibility here
I still think you have some flexibility here but I think that
the concern that I have is that if you can set the lot the setback anywhere you want it and if you can measure lot width wherever you want it you're going to get some pretty strange gerrymandered lots
I saw an email from you indicating that your feeling that at least based on your experience was that it means exactly 50 feet, not at least 50 feet, but 50 feet.
And
I can certainly understand that.
I'm just looking for something here to see if I have it on screen which I may not.
No, I'm sorry I thought I had something I could share with you. Did a sketch for jim
in which
I
just drew now here it is
can I share a screen for one mr chairman
yes go ahead
let's see if it'll let me do that
share screen okay let's see if we can get to the one I want
yes
can see I wasn't good at artwork
but
road road
50 foot setback?
This a little smaller so you can see the whole thing.
And
50 foot setback if it says at least 50
so there's a lot with 200 feet measured more than 50
there's another one with the lot width measured at more than 50
then there's one at 50, then another one more than
50, then another one more than at 50, then another more than 50.
If
we say that the measurement of lot width is at least at the building line at least 50 feet, then you could create the light layout that I am showing you here. And that would be all those lots would meet minimum lot width and none of them would be would be rear lots.
I wasn't I was I did feel the last meeting the commission had some discretion I still do still do but this is my concern.
This is why I said if this is why I did not give you a definitive answer
on whether or not it was at least versus at the 50 foot building line
but this is my concern if it's read that way.
I'll stop sharing at that point. So I think the threshold decision for the Commission is when it says measured at the building line in this case 50 feet does that mean at,
does it mean at least?
I think you have discretion as I've said several times but I don't want to be quoted as telling you that it says at least because it doesn't say that it's not what it says you may choose to read it that way but it doesn't say that and it is within your discretion to decide
and
Jim I know you sent me an email with some concerns about that or if you have anything to add But I guess that's the decision of the commission's. How do you measure a lot with?
>> Okay. Thank you, Attorney Branch. And
I'd just like to read the definition of a rear lot from our zoning reg, Section 4.9.2,
a lot in one of the foresight zones with less than the required lot width on the accepted town road or a new road depicted on an approved subdivision.
And so if
you look at the definition
of the building lot line, it also after it talks about the 200 foot width,
anything that doesn't have that at
the building lot line
would be a rear lot. And so
going both ways,
my assessment there is that what we really have or what we are trying to create
is a rear lot.
As I said, if we left the lot lines exactly as they are now,
we could
continue
on and most likely agree
with
your plan for building
in the flood prone zone.
It's only because that was a special permit and came to the Commission with the
site plan
that we're
having to
render a decision on
the appropriateness
of the lot design
as well.
So I guess,
do any other commission members have
any comments
at that point?
Okay. I know Mr. Parkington
earlier
was trying to make a comment.
Do you have anything you'd like to add at this point, Mr. Parkington?
>> I'm just a little confused that the Phillips are being given so much trouble
to not
to I
get the impression that they're
being held up and refused
an application to build a home where they want to build it.
And I believe that a lot of the problem is relative to this little wedge
that
bounds the front of what is considered the frontage of their property, but is not frontage
because it's town property that's between them and Hendy Road. Am I correct in assuming that?
You are correct. Yes.
Well, if they own
>> For the record, Mr. Chairman, Mr. Parking is correct that the issue is measurement of lot width.
Mr. Parking is not correct that the Commission has held this up. This did not comply with flood zone, it did not comply with use zone. There's been a variance issued. There have been issues with this from the very beginning and I think the Commission has all the town agencies have moved quite expeditiously.
Plans that have been submitted to us have been changed repeatedly.
The initial plan submitted didn't show a lot with at all,
the
information provided here has been inadequate from day one and I think the Commission and its staff have gone out of their way to try to help the Phillips to find a way through this
with very little information from the outbreak. So that I have to correct. You.
Thank you very
I apologize.
>> I apologize. I probably used the
wrong words and or terminology.
But
it just seems unfortunate to me that it's taken them as long as it has to try
to accomplish what they've been trying to accomplish when it appears to me that they've they've done everything that they need to to
try to accomplish what they're trying to accomplish.
>> Mr. Parkington, my only feedback on that is we probably could have concluded this issue
a month ago
if the Phillips had
decided to leave the lot lines as they currently exist.
Okay.
>> By choosing to redraw the lot lines
that we're getting ourselves
into
a bit of a dilemma.
>> Okay.
Also my understanding was
during
the last meeting,
I was under the impression that what was going to be addressed last month was the issue of the flood zone
and what the regulations
governed on what could or could not be done
in a flood plain.
And it seemed to me that none of that was addressed at all last month.
>> I
feel that we addressed
all of those issues
to my satisfaction last month.
The Phillips has had a
very
good documentation of what the requirements were out of our zoning regs and their
ability to comply with
those requirements.
So I was satisfied
without a lot of time taken on that issue
that
they did meet the requirements there.
It's only because they are trying to create
a lot
different from what currently exists
in that different lot does not comply,
in my mind, with our zoning regulations
that we got ourselves into
the dilemma.
>> Okay.
So we're just the biggest problem then for the Phillips then is just lot lines.
The floodplain is not an issue. That's already been agreed on that they can develop there as long as the lot lines are acceptable to town regulation?
>> It has not been agreed upon.
They
made their case.
Once we complete the public hearing,
then the commission would deliberate
on the application that was presented to us.
And since we had no questions on
that,
my suspicion is that the Commission would vote favorably on it. I cannot speak for the other Commission members
on how they would vote in that case.
I can only
say that we did not,
at the request of the applicant,
close the public hearing and take a vote.
Okay.
I would just like
I'm sorry.
Oh, go ahead.
>> I would just like to
make a statement in regard to the
application
regarding their special permit to construct a single family home in the flood zone.
If
the way I feel if the Phillips want to build and if they're willing to assume the responsibility
for
and
I use the word
very loosely.
They assumed the responsibility
for possible
flood damage.
I support their plans and the request.
I believe in the that the bridge that exists now
for the past thirty seven years
has pretty much controlled any kind of a possible flood problem.
And my understanding
is
what they propose to build,
which I understand does not involve
a basement,
they're just planning on building on a slab.
I don't foresee any flood problem.
The volume of water that the
existing bridge carries
doesn't act as a dam as the old one did to
potentially flood this whole area,
which is something that I used to deal with thirty seven years ago. I used to have water in my basement.
Ever since that bridge was put in, I no longer have a problem.
And I feel the Phillips are going to have no problem as well.
And
one more statement that I would like to make that the Phillips
not only
acquired
that piece of property that they're planning to build on, they also acquired
the property directly across the road from me.
And
what I have seen them do with that particular home in the last couple of years,
I am very pleased. I am very impressed with.
And if I can expect the same thing to happen with anything they propose
next door to that existing house,
they have all of my support because I like what I see. They do nice work.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Parkington, for providing
that statement on the record.
And
I don't disagree with
anything that
you have said there.
And so
is there anybody else from the public that would
like to provide a comment? And I don't know that I see anybody else that
might be interested in making the statement at that point.
Hearing none, I would go back to the applicants
to if there's anything else that you want to provide to the Commission on the record before we
move to close the public hearing?
Hearing none,
I would
accept
a motion from
the
Commission Member to
close the public hearing.
>> I can hear you here. Unmuted.
Tom was trying to get everybody's attention. I think he wanted to say something quickly. Oh, I'm sorry. Yeah, I didn't see.
Go ahead, Tom. He's coming over to my seat.
>> I just think we're having some technical difficulties on one of the computers here.
I was just asking for one second, Mr. Chairperson, if we can mute for a second and just speak and come right back on.
Yeah, go ahead. Okay, thanks.
>> Okay, we have no further comments.
Thank you for waiting for us. Okay.
>> And
before
I
get the motion to close the public hearing, I would like to say
that
in particular
to the Phillips
that I agree with Mr. Parkinson's comment on all the good work that's been done on that property
over there.
And
I view the dilemma that I'm in is not one where
it can be based at all in what I'd like to do.
I and each of the commission members have a sworn obligation
to comply with our zoning regulations.
And so
it's not what I'd like to do. It's what,
in this case, I feel
that I have to do.
And so
just like to make that clear.
I'll
go back to
looking for a motion to close the public hearing.
I'll move to close the public hearing.
Thank you, Commissioner Prasad.
I second it.
>> Thank you, Vice Chairman Cremay.
Any discussion?
Okay, a call for a roll call vote. Vice Chairman Cremay?
Aye.
Commissioner Prasad?
Commissioner Arneson?
Aye.
Commissioner Hutchinson.
>> And I vote aye as well. Motion carries five zero zero.
The public hearing is closed at 07:28.
And at this point, I will open
the regular planning and zoning meeting.
Roll call seating of alternates.
I see Vice Chairman Cremay,
Commissioner Hutchinson,
Commissioner Persson,
myself
and I will seek alternate Commissioner Arneson
for Commissioner Englund.
Next is the additions or changes to the agenda.
And I would like to move up
the application under old business to 57 Hendy Road
to be the first order
of the old business.
And that is the only change
I would like to make.
Anybody else have any other changes they would like to make to the agenda?
Hearing
none,
I would like anybody
who is opposed to the change I just made to the agenda
to
let me know. Otherwise, I will consider that you have voted in favor for it. Are there any opposed?
Any abstain?
And the agenda is changed by a vote of five-zero-zero.
Any additional public comment before we proceed on to old business?
Hearing none I'll move on to old business.
And the first
item we'll take is the application of 57
Hendy Road.
And again, at this point,
only those seated commissioners
can participate in the deliberation
that we have
on the application.
Do any of the commissioners have any comments to make
on the application
presented? On
Hearing none.
I'm looking for a motion comments to approve the application
>> I'll move to approve the application
for 57 Hendy Road.
>> Thank
you, Vice Chairman for me looking for a second
And again, the reason for
making the motion to approve the application,
even if you have concerns about that,
is because we always want a motion
in a positive sense
in the event that it were to be disapproved,
then we would clearly have
the action taken on the motion.
If we made a motion to the negative
and the motion didn't pass, then we're not exactly sure where we are. So that's why I'm looking for
the positive motion before we have any discussion
to approve the application 57 Hendy Road. And I'm looking for a second at that point.
And I'll second.
>> Thank
you, Commissioner Arneson.
Any discussion on the application?
Okay.
Hearing none,
I'll call for a roll call vote.
Vice Chairman Cremay.
I vote aye.
Commissioner Persson.
No.
Commissioner Hutchinson.
Aye.
Commissioner Arneson?
Vote no.
>> And I vote no as well.
The motion
fails,
three opposed.
The opposition
is
myself,
Commissioner Persson,
and Commissioner Arneson.
My recommendation to the Phelps
again,
there were a lot of ways to proceed since you own all the property.
My recommendation
is
that you leave the lot lines as they are get approval to build the house.
Because we
went to a vote as opposed to withdrawing the motion,
well, I guess it would take
it's going to take a new special permit no matter how you
look at it because
the existing special permit was
for something that was just approved. So
unfortunately,
this is what's going to make the process take a little bit longer
and it's proceeding as expeditiously
as possible
by the Commission.
So with that, that completes the first item of business.
Move on to the next item of business
is the application of Joseph Mott,
Wales Road.
And at this point I would ask
Mr. Mott if
you want to
I see you added a new site plan
to our
listing on the website.
If you'd like to walk us through that, that would be great.
>> Yeah. So basically the addition
was
we had talked about the
driveway didn't include the driveway
to the rear garage, which was added and the SNE plan
was included on the
plot plan,
just showing the silt fence line
and storage of materials, which was asked for.
>> I am going to try and share my screen
and pull up
the drawing that
Mr. Mahd is referring to.
Okay, go ahead Mr. Mike.
>> As you can see the self fence and the storage of materials
have been added to the plan as well as the driveway to the rear garage.
The only other comment that we had last week was about the square footage,
which I believe we were
incorrect in stating that it did not meet the square footage.
The inside dimensions of the apartment
do fall under 800 square feet.
Okay.
>> Anything else you want to tell us about your application
tonight?
At this time.
No, not at this time. Okay.
>> Agent Halsey,
do you have any comments on the application?
>> Sure.
Joe had
the ENS plan as you indicated in the driveway.
As far as the dimensions of the apartment,
I had utilized the
exterior
dimensions. Od.
Regulations are silent on the on the matter.
So, recalculating using the interior,
it does come in
just under 800 square feet.
Again, there's no there's no the
regulations are not are not specific one way or the other.
Am I still on? Yes,
>> I'm done. You caught me by surprise.
And so
I was just checking my regulations.
I thought our regulation said
800 square feet gross
floor area,
which would be
measured external.
But as
you just indicated, Agent Halsey, it says between two fifty and eight hundred square feet.
And less than 33%
of the gross floor area, the single family dwelling.
So did you confirm on that, HN
>> calculation comes into under 800 square feet? I believe it comes under seven ninety
six or seven ninety four, seven ninety six, yes, I did. Okay.
Using the inside dimensions.
>> Very good.
I thought it was a small area outside
dimensions but but as you say the
the regulation
doesn't specify one way or the other.
Chairman.
>> Mr. Chairman. Mr. Branch. Yeah for the record Mark Branch I'm
just I'm a little confused here I have the regulation in front of me I see I believe doesn't it say gross floor area?
>> Well I was just
looking at that and as I
>> Oh.
See 8B, the gross floor area of the accessory unit shall be between two fifty and eight hundred square feet.
>> You are correct, Attorney Branson. And that's why I don't like to make decisions on the fly during these meetings because
even when I did my homework, I was questioning myself there. It does say gross floor area. And you Which is an external measurement.
>> And the gross floor area is defined in section 24 as being the exterior walls.
>> That is correct. You're right. My mistake. I apologize. So
>> it does now
it also mentioned under that definition of gross floor area
that you didn't have to count the stairwell.
And that's why I was going to ask Mr. Mott for how he
arrived at his
calculation
there. But if you
do the 800 or you do the
I'm trying to read there
the dimensions on it. 26 by
38,
I think
that came out to well
in excess of 900
square feet.
And
so I do
agree with Attorney Branch that we should be measuring that externally
to the addition that you want to put on and that needs to be jimmy:
Below the 800 square feet.
>> Now I have a question and a solution for that. The question
is part of the
gross area of the garage, the addition that I'd be putting on is going to be a closet for the existing house.
That would be subtracted from the gross apartment,
I'm assuming.
I
did not read it that way.
Because that will not be accessible
from the apartment.
>> But it is, well,
I understand.
But gross square footage is measured externally
on the addition that you're trying to put on there. So
by virtue of the fact that you're building the closet in there, I was not able to convince myself that that met the intent of
the gross square footage calculation.
>> Well, one question Mr. Chairman,
that closet, did I hear the applicant say that it would not be accessible from the
accessory apartment.
That's correct.
Correct. That's
That's
>> It does not include it doesn't exclude correct. Closets.
However,
I'm
measure the exterior faces of the walls
or from the center line
of party or common walls
separating two buildings dwellings
or distinct and separate not well it's not residential areas so if that closet
has a common wall with the new apartment that is accessible only from the existing house
I think it measured the center line of that common wall and I think you could deduct the closet
from the accessory apartment and if that gives you compliance and you 're,
only have two screens, I can't view the reg and the diagram. But I think that if the closet
is part of the main house, is it mean, even though it's part of the addition, if it's only accessible to the main house, I don't think you should count it for the accessory apartment and maybe that gets them where it needs to be.
>> Yeah it doesn't bring them below it doesn't bring it into compliance no.
Still doesn't?
>> Anyway I would still be about 60 feet outside
I believe.
>> I thought one of the options you were looking at last month when we got together Mr. Mott was
taking two
feet off the length of the
garage.
>> Yes, it was.
However, when I was just
by measuring the inside dimension got me within the 800, therefore I didn't
pursue it further.
But now
knowing that it's the outside dimensions of the exterior walls,
I will have to bump the
front wall of the 2nd Floor in
to
the
maximum
>> size I'm allowed. This Jim House, just for clarity,
Jed, you had said shorten the garage. He's not in fact shortening the garage, he's shortening the 2nd Floor of the garage. So the apartment area.
I just want to make sure that that's clear.
The footprint of the garage would remain the same. The footprint could,
>> it might be more difficult to
make
it
not all one continuous
wall.
Certainly,
I think my guess is that the size of the garage was chosen to maximize the space in the apartment,
not because you needed to squeeze two cars into something that's 38 feet long.
I'm
just guessing on that, but
the question for the applicant is to show
a
apartment
that is less than 800
gross square feet.
>> So
currently it would measure eight fifty six.
I was correct in assuming that the stairs are not included or they are included?
The
stairway
>> portion is not included. Okay, so yeah, we're at 856.
Would
minus
there's a void space behind the toilet that it's six square feet.
I would
like to bump the front wall of only the apartment, only the 2nd Floor into
the addition two feet to
accomplish
the
800 square foot maximum.
The garage will remain the same size.
>> Okay.
What I'd like to do is
find out what other questions the commission has and
we can circle back to
the square footage of the apartment. If we need to, we can vote on the application
with the condition that you have to show
and get agreement with agent Halsey that there's less than 800 square feet
in that. Is that agreeable
to you Mr. Mai?
>> I just want
to
know that I
did have this conversation with Joe
regarding bumping back the 2nd Floor and he's thought out the framing detail
as to how that would be accomplished. So it's not something that is just redesigning
on the fly.
There was some fourth thought that went into it. He's conscious of
the fact,
how it would be framed. That's what I'm saying. So that's
all.
Okay.
>> So I'm not sure I captured whatever
the point was you were trying to make on that, Agent Allison.
>> Well, I just wanted you to know it wasn't a decision they made on the fly. It's something that he had given
some forethought to and understands how the construction is going to occur.
Hi. Something that can happen. I initially thought that it would be, you know, he talked about a beam and
the beam appeared to me to be in the middle of a stairway.
And in fact, the beam of which he speaks is really an integral part of the floor framing and it's not an issue.
>> So are you saying we would
be better served to have the applicant come back in a month with a more clear
depiction of the 800 square foot? No, I'm comfortable with
>> that amount of seating.
I just wanted to be clear that
it was thought out.
The
alternative plan was
not conceived this evening. Was
thought out and the framing detail was discussed. Okay, I got you. I understand.
>> Are there any
other commission members have any
comments
about the application?
Alternate Commissioner
Blanchard,
since we are done with the deliberations on the public hearing,
is an alternate,
at this point you're able to ask questions on the application
as well if you had any.
Hearing no other questions, I would like to just ask
the applicant, and I know Agent Halsey last
month
mentioned that the addition of the accessory apartment shall not alter the basic character of the dwelling as a single family residence.
And I was just interested
in
if Mr. Mike you had any comments on
how to
keep
character of the house that you currently have.
My
only concern with that is I have seen where
we have added on to a couple of houses
in
one of the cases
The
house went from what I thought was a very nice small home
to what looked like a big warehouse.
Jimmy: And I was hoping that that would not be the case,
although the size of this garage that you're looking to put right next to your house there is
probably as big as the house itself. And so
it does have, if it's not
thought of a little bit,
it does have the
potential to
>> look out of place in the neighborhood, if you will. Absolutely.
When
I was thinking about building a garage, I kind of had two options. One was to add on to the existing house and the other was to put up a detached garage in the rear, basically where the only other
feasible spot would be. And originally I had wanted to do a
steel building
and I really felt like that would detract from the rest of the neighborhood. So to keep this
looking like a single family style house, it's going to match all the windows are going to match the house, which is drawn on the plan to show that the same size as what is a traditional
single family home.
The overhang is going to be the exact same as the house. The siding is going to be the same as the house.
The garage doors are going to match the house.
Everything down to the trim from the outside is going to be matching the house as well as the inside. The garage is going to be the same design from the inside as the existing garage and the apartment is going to be the same design as the rest of the house. So inside and out, it's the same as the existing house. It is large.
It's definitely not as large as the existing house is now. The existing house is
eight feet longer and
at least a foot wider,
but
it is going to add a substantial amount of space onto the house.
>> Okay,
thank you. And Agent Halsey, I just have one last question for you.
The accessory apartment
in the one we're talking now is probably the first of many that we're gonna see.
I know when we crafted the
regulations
we had two
concepts in mind. One was
the
detached accessory apartment
and we talked about
it's a house not a shed
and it should be treated as such.
And then I think we had in mind
setting off
a portion of the existing
house
is an accessory apartment within the existing structure.
We didn't really, at least I didn't foresee
that we were going to
craft something right
adjacent to it to make it part of the primary
dwelling.
Although there's no reason that
we shouldn't think that. I just don't think that we did when we came up with that. So my question is,
is the nature of the drawings that the applicant provided for this something that would be consistent
with
what would be presented to the building
official
for building a house?
Yes.
Okay.
I just wanted to make sure that we were
building a house
and not a shed when we put it right next door there.
He provided pretty details. He did.
>> Thought
it
was
quite thorough and
I saw all the things I was looking for in there.
And that will be a standard that we shoot for in follow on applications. Okay, so anyhow, I think that's all
the questions that
I had.
Is there somebody that would like to make a motion
a motion that, concerning
>> the application at 141 Wales Road? I just have one question for you Jed.
Yep, go ahead.
>> Did we go over the percentage of the house versus the accessory apartment
square footage? And what's the regulation? Is it 33?
>> We
did not, as part of the hearing here,
the requirement is it can be no more than 33%
of the gross square footage of the
primary.
Notes up another question. So what I did
is I went to the record card for the house. It had
something
of
maybe 1,500 square feet of net floor area.
And then I read the regulation again and it said gross floor area and that said 2,000
something. And so the calculation
based on 2,000 was
well within
that amount.
Okay, that's good. What I did not do
is
by the addition that we're putting on,
we have
changed both the net square footage of the primary dwelling
and the gross square footage of the primary dwelling. Dwelling.
I didn't add those two together to see if 800 was more than one third of that.
But since the square footage went up,
I guess it can't.
It just doesn't work that way. So I
did check that
the
33%
limit was not exceeded in this case.
>> Right, another question I have Jed is,
was there anything when we did the regulation,
was it relative to the number
of occupants versus the amount of parking spaces?
>> Our regulation says that
we need to have two parking spots for primary residence and one for the accessory apartment,
which he has.
And how about an as built or the
foundation?
>> I
looked at his drawings and it had a fair amount of detail on the foundation.
I did not see anything
in the as built and
because it's an attached
accessory apartment,
we didn't get into the special permitting which would have required
the as built drawing. So I think we're okay with respect to that.
Because it wasn't a special permit,
based my review, you're pretty much on the requirements specified in section
4.11,
our regulations.
Because
it's attached?
>> Yes.
And that was the
purpose of my question. Do these drawings,
are they similar to what we would expect for somebody coming in and building And a
I did think that
Mr. Mott, when I was looking down through the
foundation details, the whole bit,
there was
a significant amount of detail in there and I thought
he had it covered.
Any other questions, Scott?
No.
Okay,
>> so we're back to looking for a motion to approve the application
at 141 Wales Road.
>> I would like to make a motion to approve the application
for an accessory apartment on 142 Wales Road.
As long as everything
goes through
Jim as far as the square footage
requirement.
>> Mr. Chairman. Yes, attorney branch. May I just share my screen for a moment. Yes.
>> Okay see if that fills the bill for you.
Left out a T.
Mr. Mahat, is your address 142 or 141?
142.
Okay,
>> because on the That's what was on the agenda. That's what I used. Yep,
on the application
oh,
>> was agent Halsey's comments there. Think he was okay. Remember that. Okay. And I think you said which wall but I didn't catch which one it was. I just put one wall.
Maybe it doesn't matter which wall.
And by the way, remember the stairwell only be one wall.
And the
stairwell
does not count for growth gross floor area.
Correct. Okay. Sounds
good.
Okay, did we have a second?
Does this mover want to use this?
>> Can, can
you put identify that as something and they can just identify it as your,
put a number or something on there Mark, and I can just instead of reading the whole thing
>> how do you mean I mean I can I was gonna put
>> a put a title on it put a title on it
hang on
Look okay? Yeah.
Thank you. Attorney branch.
>> I will do all the motions but I thought this was complicated enough you want but you might want some help. No, I appreciate that. Okay.
I'll second the motion.
>> Thank you, Vice Chairman Cremay.
Any other discussion on the application?
Hearing none,
a call for a vote. Vice Chairman Cremay?
Aye.
Commissioner
Persaud?
Aye.
Commissioner
Hutchinson?
>> Hi I just have a quick question if that's okay at this point.
Go ahead. It's just about the motion it's not about the application itself. Oh go ahead Leanne.
Ask your question.
>> Are you there? Yes.
Okay. Do we we don't need to read the motion as presented by attorney Branson to the record?
Scott moved to approve it it was seconded but is that sufficient
since since now we have a draft motion?
>> Then I'm certainly happy to read it if you have any any doubts.
>> Oh, no, no, not, not since you're here I was just wondering. It's normally something we would do but you're not normally here so if we don't need.
>> Yes, I
think because
the motion is up on the screen
that
suffices
and if we can get Attorney Grants to
email that motion
to
Commissioner Hallisey and our board clerk so that we can get it properly into our minutes
also to
Jed anybody else you want to add?
>> I'll give it to Mindy.
All right. Need some board clerk I'm sorry.
All right. So it is
in your box now.
Okay.
>> Okay, thank you. I think we left it. So moving on
to our vote, Vice Chairman Crevay.
Aye.
Commissioner Persson.
Commissioner Hutchinson.
Aye.
Commissioner Arneson.
>> And I vote aye as well. Motion passes five,
zero, zero.
So Mr. Mott, once you
get your
agreement with Commissioner Halsey on the 800 square feet
and you see the approval of the motion
in the
online or in the River East,
you have to wait fifteen days for somebody to come in and appeal the motion before you can actually start building.
Okay.
And that completes
that one.
Thank you.
>> Next on the agenda is the application of George
Korea and Eric Melissa
Lodiceka,
Wolf Farms Road Pine Ridge Drive.
I apologize for the mispronunciations
on your names there.
I know
>> that
we still do not have the
inland wetlands approval
for your application.
One of the things that,
well I guess, you know, we'll do
any commission members have any
questions
of the applicants
at this point?
And I've got just
a
couple of comments here.
Did not see in,
you submitted a very thorough application
all under application,
it just goes on and on and on with all kinds of good stuff.
Commissioner
Halsey, I did not see our
special permit
checklist
with all of the stuff that was online
today.
I honestly thought that was on
>> there. So
there's two.
The application
looks like it's got a listing of things to be submitted.
I think that's outdated.
I think if you look in Section 23,
it tells you to submit the zoning
checklist which is the 67
>> item review or something. I believe Eric and I had gone over the 57.
It's 57 items. 57, Heinz. So we had gone over, yes, we had gone over it. Okay.
I have not had a chance to review it in its entirety as yet. Okay. I was
assuming that I was
hoping that the commission could set a public hearing on it.
>> Well, we very well may. I just want to make sure that when we get together at the next meeting that we have the checklist that's reviewed
by you and you're
consistent, you agree with it and we have it
a week ahead of time so that we can do our due diligence review of the checklist. And then spend
a lot of The time going through
>> only thing that
was
not provided
was it's actually a deed restriction for the conservation
subdivision.
When Eric and I had initially gone over the
checklist,
I had indicated that was not applicable. I didn't think of that particular
easement. Then we had a subsequent conversation
and I brought it to his attention. He did submit,
they discussed using
one that's already been in use by the town and modifying it just for the sake of ease. And he did provide that without, and he hasn't had a chance to modify it as yet.
No less is aware of
the fact that one is required.
>> Okay.
And as I recall back to an earlier application that you and I worked on where we didn't have that done ahead of time,
that got to be problematic at some point. So it is important that we have that
complete before we
approve the application.
The other
comment I
saw is that
on
rear lots,
you need to have the fire marshal
review
and approve
your driveway
turnaround so they can bring in an emergency vehicle. And I did not see on your drawings
a comment that
it didn't look to me like there was a
turnaround at the end of your driveways to support
bringing a fire truck in or something and
having it be able to turn around to get back out.
So agent Halsey can work with you to get the fire marshal to review what your proposal is, but I think it's important that you have that.
And
then agent Halsey
mentioned
the possibility,
the potential of a sidewalk.
And I
think that's a good idea.
Any of the other commission members
got any thoughts on that?
>> I think it sounds like a good idea.
Yeah, I agree.
>> So does that mean that you're going to make a motion that we have a sidewalk?
A motion that
we have a sidewalk.
What
day?
>> Well, we'll have a discussion after we get the motion on the floor.
>> All right. And I motion to have a site law.
>> Is there a second to that motion?
I'll second. Okay, thank you.
And that was Commissioner Persson made the motion.
Commissioner Arneson
seconded the motion. Discussion
at this point,
we normally
do the site visits on a Saturday morning.
Doesn't mean it has to be that way.
But that's worked out pretty well for us.
I
have a little bit of a conflict this Saturday morning where if we were to do it, I would like to do it earlier rather than later.
Or I don't know how everybody feels about doing it on the Saturday of Memorial Day weekend
or we could even push it off until
Saturday, June 5. Our next meeting isn't until
the '20 So
>> we've got
five
weeks of time between now and then. We've got plenty of time.
But I would prefer to do it either the twenty ninth through June 5.
Anybody else have one
of those days that's
not convenient for you?
>> Can't do May 29. I could do June 5. Okay.
Is
are the applicants
okay with June 5
June 5 would work for me
>> so if you were to say it for me yes
June 5, well, and I remember we did actually do
a site visit via Zoom on the last one.
Attorney Brandt, I would like you to stay
on for
the rest of the meeting tonight. We've got a couple issues coming up
and we'll deal
with that. Let I
can't remember which one it is, but I know there's something else out there that's coming.
So I would propose
that we amend the motion to have the sidewalk
on June 5 at 09:00.
That sounds good.
>> Okay, so
Commissioner Persson has amended the motion to make it June 5 nine a. M. A second to that?
Commissioner Artisan, are you ready to second that one again? Yeah, I'll second that. Okay,
so there's the motion on the floor that we do a sidewalk June 5 at 09:00.
Any further discussion?
Hearing none,
Commissioner Cremay?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Persson? Aye.
Commissioner Hutchinson?
Aye.
Commissioner Arneson?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. The motion to conduct the sidewalk
carries five zero zero.
So where about will we meet?
>> We will meet
on
Pine Ridge.
And you go down to the cul de sac at the end and there's plenty of parking alongside the road. That's where we met for the Inland Wetlands
sidewalk. That worked out well.
This
time for the applicants,
with the Inland Wetlands walkthrough
sidewalk,
we focus primarily on the driveway.
I would like to
go up and
walk the entire property so that we can take a look at
you're planning to
build each of the houses,
show us where you're looking for the open space easements
to be.
And the other comment I had on
your site plan,
I did not see an extent of clearing
for the trees indicated on that. And we've had a couple of issues where
what's been on the drawing and what's been cleared have been different. And so I'd like to at least have a starting point on how much of the property you'd like to
clear tree wise
so we can get that on the drawing and
all agree on that.
Are that one still flagged up there, Jed?
>> I don't know. I'd have to ask the applicants. I assume they are. They were the last time I was there. Yes, they're
flagged.
>> And will the will the house be flagged or the location of the proposed building?
It will not.
But we have the general area.
>> Is it possible between now and June 5 that you could put a couple of stakes in the ground where where the houses would be going?
Yes.
Okay.
And the septic system?
>> Clearing lines, how about the, is there something in there about trees over 10 inches?
There is on the checklist.
Is the idea.
>> What is that
What is it with the 10 inches trees?
>> The
intention is to
not be cutting
trees greater than 10 inches in diameter.
Now, if there was one that,
if there's
I don't recall the trees being that big up on your lot there.
We don't want to lose all the big trees. You obviously can't have them where
your house is going to go and that's the purpose of the flagging of
septic in the house and that sort of thing is so we can just review that.
>> Well, I can say that our intention is to cut the least amount of trees
that are required in order for us to get the house and to get the septic system in the driveway in place. Want to maintain as much of the
natural
wooded area as possible.
Yep, understand.
Okay, no worries. Yep.
>> There
have been occasions where we've heard that before and that's not what happened.
>> Yeah, I feel like when I built my house, they took down a lot more trees than we'd expected.
Yep. Beyond where
the septic was,
beyond where the house was.
These guys start cutting trees, they just cut them.
>> I have seen that on essentially every application to build a house since I've been on the commission.
And so that's why yeah,
nice to have that discussion ahead of time. Be nice if we could get it right. Yep, we'll keep working at it. Yeah, I mean, as far as those,
>> you know,
we're just going to clear as much so that we don't have
roots
coming in and destroying the septic system in the future.
And
also,
you any
large trees that are gonna be near the potential where the houses are gonna be,
we'll probably wanna cut those down so that we don't have a case of a windstorm
in the future, we don't have trees falling on the house.
>> Understand.
Yep. And
that makes sense.
We would all agree that that is a reasonable approach.
Do the applicants have any other questions for the commission at this point?
I do not.
>> Okay.
We will see you at 09:00 on June 5.
Moving on to the
next item, the application
>> Just
make sure to post that, Jim, as a meeting of the commission in the clerk's office.
>> Yes, absolutely.
But no public
hearing has been set as of yet.
>> Oh,
good point. I do want to schedule the public hearing. Thank you.
So on that,
and
again, we've got,
we currently have
ninety days
extension of timeframes
because of the COVID,
but I don't want to use that
in the next, our next meeting because we're five weeks
out here at this point comes sixty
three days after you submitted your application.
And so
would
entertain a motion that we schedule the public hearing
for the next meeting which is
June 21.
And
if per chance,
my
thinking is that the inland wetlands decision
hopefully will be made tomorrow night, will come through that.
And so
if we weren't able to hold a public hearing, we'd cross that
when we get there.
But
at this point, I would
think it prudent to assume
that we will be able to go to public hearing and if something changes,
we'll just not do a public hearing. That'd be easy enough. So I would like
to have a motion that we hold public hearing at the next zoning meeting on June 21.
So moved.
>> Thank you, Leigh Ann. Is there a second? I'll second that. Thank you, Scott. Any
discussion on holding the public hearing?
Hearing none, call for a vote.
Vice Chairman Cremay?
You're muted. I can see your lips. I.
Thank you. Commissioner Persson? I.
Commissioner Arneson.
Sorry, guilty by the same offense. Aye. Commissioner
>> Hutchinson.
Aye. And I vote aye as well. The motion passes five-zero-zero.
Okay. That completes the business that I wanted to get done on that one tonight.
And thank you for helping me get that scheduled.
The
next item is the application of Chris Bell
for the gravel
operation located at 517 Route 6.
And at this point,
Mr. Bell,
do you have your drawing that you can share screen or do you need me
to call up the drawing so that you can walk us through that? Let me see. Can everybody hear me? Yes.
>> Okay. Let me see if I can
get it up on my screen.
Can everybody see that? Yes.
Okay.
Very good.
I'm surprised I was able to do that so easy. Okay,
my name is Chris Bell. I'm a professional engineer from Higginham
representing
the applicant William Genovese.
What you see here
is a
colored up
site plan,
the
former site plan
S2,
which shows
the stations,
100 foot stations coming from
basically the street line,
the station zero all the way to the back of the property.
I went out there
about two weeks ago this Friday
and
took some site pictures and also took some measurements
to the
different status of
sand and gravel operations that are there right now.
The
gravel pit operation
was basically started
between
Station 250 and 350,
and has proceeded and proceeded going
west until it got to the other side of the property
as it goes towards
the parts building.
And
during this operation,
they have
made a
pile here you see in red,
that is a sifted sand
location,
and that is
moving
right now. They actually have taken a third of that, that's about a thousand cubic yards, they've taken about
300 cubic yards out of that in the last week.
These numbers here that you see in the white area,
this is the area that has been
disturbed in the property. This was brought down to an Elevation 294
to
construct the detention basin,
and then the access road comes back here and circles around here. These elevations are approximate
to the nearest half a foot or so, Elevation 295,
295, 295.
The goal is to get the elevation two ninety four and a half,
the, or two ninety four, and then bring in four to six inches of topsoil on top of that to get above the floodplain. The floodplain in this area is about
just under two ninety four.
The Hop River is back in this area
along the north western side of the property.
The area I show here in brown
are the areas of topsoil,
as was designated on the plan to be stored in this area.
There's about 1,300
cubic yards here. There's a small
portion of topsoil here, about two twenty yards,
and a small portion of ungraded sand gravel.
Now these two piles here were going to be
spread across this area for final grading. Once this area in yellow is taken down to two ninety five,
it's going to be spread here to degrade the property and do any other grading
back here
from our meeting that we're going to have
with Hank Gruner and
the same members that were out a couple weeks ago with Jim Halsey.
Right now we are, we've realized that the contractor has put
tree stumps in this back area
and stored them back there, which was not part of
the deal. It was not supposed to put them there. We're in the process of taking those out right now.
We've got about
25 to 30% of them out as of today.
We have an
agreement with
a person to be taking them out and taking them off-site
within the next two weeks.
Right now,
we couldn't get
that 20 five-thirty percent off-site, so we've taken them and moved them out to the front area so they can be transported out much quicker. We just want to get them out of this area,
and as I said, well,
the goal is to get them out
in the next two weeks. There's about,
in total about four tractor trailer loads of stumps that are back there, and we'll immediately restore that site as soon as the stumps are out.
The goal after that is to finish the,
during the next two weeks, is to remove this area
of grade so we can final grade the back area and have the meeting
with,
again, with Jim
Halsey and
Hank Rooner to
go over exactly how they want to
restore this site as far as plantings, moguls,
and the like for
the back area.
Once
that is completed and graded and restored,
we will then continue to
go to the next site,
which is up here, and remove this original grade.
As part of this application,
sent in, I wanted to wait till today to submit
a schedule,
which I gave to Jim Halsey
this afternoon,
which is as close as I can get to what the schedule should be
if
the Commission does approve the extension for the next six months.
If you'd like, I could
put that schedule on
the board right now, unless I have
some other questions about the site here.
>> I'd like to
continue the discussion on
the overall plan
at this point before
we bring that letter up.
>> All right, again, well,
goal here is to hold this topsoil area and use that for restoration
for
the
phases as we head towards the front,
as was required by
the approval to start from the back and head towards the front. So this topsoil
will get smaller and smaller as we get closer to the front,
and then this will all get restored
along with
the end phase down here that's around the detention pond.
And once all the grading is complete
and topsoil is spread
with seed and mulch,
we will restore
the detention basin
to a more permanent status.
It was recommended that we keep the detention basin there for
the future use of the property
since it's all going to grade towards that area. We'll
grade this out
with a more permanent topsoil and plantings.
Again, we'll discuss what we'll do at the time, but basically, you know, just topsoil and seed it and
add in any extra plantings around there
as the Commission requires.
That would be towards the end of the six months.
I think
the scheduling,
as I'll go over,
is quite conservative.
We're currently removing,
we can remove about 800 cubic yards per week
because we're getting to the summer months of construction.
It's starting to move quite well. We're getting,
you know, around eight to 10 truckloads
get removed a day.
We have a
current problem that
we had thought we had fixed last Thursday. The
entrance gate
located
just beyond the apron
keeps getting knocked down. Last Thursday we put it back up and secured it, and it got knocked down again today.
We will be addressing that problem by not leaving it up to the truckers to open and close the gate.
We will have
one of the attendees
as part of the garage,
who runs the, the manager that runs the garage during the day will open the gate in the morning and then close it before he leaves in the afternoon.
That's basically one of the security
problems that we're going to be addressing
immediately.
As far as the site plan goes,
think the areas are
distinctive of where we are at this point,
and what we have to do.
In this area
there's probably about approximately 10,000 cubic yards left.
There are
a couple of spotty areas of storage materials on-site,
so we're
approximately,
I can't say, I don't think they're going to get as much material out of this as originally planned.
We might be closer to being
halfway done with some of the removal
and relocation
of materials,
and we'll be probably close to two thirds removal
as we finish up all these phases,
and we get to the last
phase.
We haven't been able to
complete
a whole phase, a whole rectangle,
because of the way of the shape of the site and the way the traffic has to go
in order to get a
turnaround
for the trucks as they back in to get loaded.
We kept a circular motion here, we would find it a little bit difficult to complete an entire phase rectangle
and restore it.
It was always the goal to complete the last phase,
the one and a half phase, like from Station 4
all the way to 565,
which is like a phase and a half. We want to complete that first with restoration
before we move any further on the site.
And
basically, that's
my presentation on the site. I would
be glad to entertain any questions.
>> Okay, thank you. Any commission members have any questions at this point?
>> What?
Yeah, I just do.
How far are you done now?
How far completed are you done?
>> I
would say that
the actual removal is about
one third.
We've tried to keep the disturbance of the phases down to less than two
as required by the approval.
And so there's
parts of some phase
being graded and removed and some parts of the phases are not. So,
I mean, realistically, we're about a third the way through.
And
we've,
most of the work has been, you know, getting the site prepped
as far as a lot of the getting rid of the debris that was on the site, getting the topsoil
all together
into one spot, and then getting
the grading operation going.
And we really got killed on last year on the COVID virus that really put everything to a halt. We had
everything ready to go
at the end of
twenty nineteen in December, and then
all the contracts that we had
going for the spring all got canceled and nothing really happened until
the fall of last year. We had some removal but there really wasn't very much last year at all. Are you done taking out material
at the elevation at 295?
>> Mostly yes.
There'll be a
final grading to make sure
we are
draining properly towards the front right now. It's pretty much dead flat.
And we
did that to just
have a drainage
go along the side of the
access road and go through what's a
stone revetment that we have here. So we wouldn't put too much strain on the silt fences. So it pretty much goes evenly across, there are a couple spaces that
the drainage does get concentrated
and we're trying to maintain that so it doesn't go through the silt fence.
But
most of it does get
back towards the basin
and to the wetlands. Because of the type A soil,
most of the water just goes straight down.
It only seems to
get drainage capability when the ground gets wet and then it freezes
during
January, February, and then which increases the runoff, but as soon as it thaws it goes right back into the ground again.
We haven't been having
any drainage problems out there.
>> Chris, I
see the area that's marked 302, so it's seven feet over.
That's correct. In that area over, what, I'm gonna carry it out. The other two areas I see are stockpiles,
there's one that's great, there's one that's graded sand that you gotta take out of there. So I see that it to me it looks like there's a whole lot more than a third done.
You get stockpiles
across most of it and you know the stump pile and you said got seven feet throughout you know maybe
an eighth or a tenth of the site.
Then the rest of it is back to the original grade, so it seems like there's a lot more. And another question I have is did the operators
put the stumps in the wetlands?
>> No, they're just
before the wetlands. If
you're out there, you can see the flags are on the other side of the silt fence,
all the flags are on the other side, so they're not in the wetlands, they are in the buffer though.
And that's what I told them when I was out there to get these out of here immediately.
Was not supposed to be any work.
>> I'm sorry? As I recall, there was not supposed to be any work in the buffer. No, there was not, sir. No, there was not. I mean, were surprised when we got out there. Mean,
I am an out And I also recall,
>> I also recall, Chris, not to cut you off, but I recall that the retention basin was supposed to be moved as you phased through this work.
Well, we had talked about,
>> you know, keeping it there and moving it. I never, nobody talked, the Commission never talked about that.
Just
when
it was approved in 06/03/2019.
>> I distinctly recalled this whole thing, the retention basin was supposed to be moved.
>> Did you want me to respond to that?
Yeah, you can. Yeah, oh yeah, it was to be moved and we also
talked about
when it was being built,
John Falente, which is known over here, he said, you know, if you can keep it at that location,
if you can provide that the drainage goes towards there and keep it there as a permanent location rather than keep moving it,
and
you know, we did do that.
You know, moving it
was not a very good option at
this time, the way we're operating this, and keeping it there,
it just seems to be a better idea for now and in the future, because the water does get there
as it goes down the access road,
and you know, we'd probably like to keep it there, I think it was a good suggestion to keep it there.
I don't see the advantage of moving it,
and it would be a disadvantage as far as the truck routes as they circle through here,
and trying to avoid it
would be rather difficult.
Right. Then we'd have to get reroute
the outlet,
and rerouting the outlet we'd have to probably go back to wetlands to reroute it up into this area as we started getting up there. We wouldn't be able to
get it all the way back to this location for the
level spreader. Right.
Thought it was idea to keep it where it was. Am I correct in the
>> assumptions,
am I reading that incorrectly, the whole
plan,
with the
amount of material
that you still have to remove, I mean to me it looks like there's seven feet in one area, the rest of it's stockpiles are stumps. To me it would be two thirds done as soon as you remove all that stuff and knock down all the topsoil.
>> As
we get all this done
and remove all of the stockpiles,
it'll get close to be, I think just over
between a half and two thirds.
I think you're correct with that.
Believe
there's about 10,000, because this is all original grade here,
this is This pretty
hasn't been removed at all.
It's all original grade,
which is,
you know, probably about 20, it's an
elevation three fourteen,
which is pretty high above here. That's another
20 feet above the existing grade.
So there is a lot of material here.
I
would think by the time this is complete and the stockpile is removed.
>> The grade towards the highway was,
is probably only 10 feet
over the grade.
Over here. Which is which is what it is you said it's three fourteen and it's two ninety four so 10 feet. The rest of it was up was up by I think it was up to three thirty or three thirty five at one spot the top of that hill.
So, think that there's a lot more than what you're saying, hey, I'm out of there, it doesn't matter to me,
just saying it doesn't, doesn't
seem
like what you're saying is
very accurate. Well,
>> know the locations are accurate, the volumes
are not exact.
I tried to estimate as best I could with the,
I moved these areas onto AutoCAD and I got areas
and then the approximate heights to get some kind of a volume.
I did not get a volume of this area, I don't think there's that much there over the course of five feet.
There's probably around another,
maybe 2,000 yards here, maybe less.
Not allowed. No, that's not allowed. This
area is almost, like I said, it's already one third gone already,
and
we have to concentrate on
finishing, you know, completely finishing this back area before we get anywhere
near this area at all. This one is not going be touched until this gets finished.
Okay.
Any other
questions?
Yes.
Go ahead, Deanne.
>> Hi. Yes. I have several questions.
Just for clarification on one of Scott's first questions
about the percent that's completed.
Were there
three or four phases originally presented?
Right.
>> Four phases, Leanne, I think. Well, were there or
Scott or someone, was it three phases, was it four phases originally, Four phases, two years
I believe.
So Mr. DeParle, no,
there's five.
>> There's five plus partly.
The last phase
is mostly regrading
into existing.
This phase back here is mostly regrading into the existing,
But there's five here. One, two, three, four, five.
Five phases?
Yes. Is that correct?
Yes.
Five phases.
>> Okay. So your answer that you're about a third done
includes
all five phases. It means you're not completely done with But we're not saying third partially done with each one? A third to a half. I'm I'm talking about volume,
>> I guess.
Had to disturb
most of the first two phases just to get the detention pond in and to get access
to the back to get it to the point where they could drive in, because this is all a hill.
So this whole area
had to get brought down
in order just to get the operation going.
So, you know, we've already
disturbed the phase, which was okay, that was part of it.
But then we started this,
working in this area, which was about halfway through the second phase and halfway into the third phase, and we did this entire phase
and we finally broke through the daylight through here so we could, you know, had a passageway
for
any vehicles that needed to come in from this side.
And then they started working back here
and started removing this.
And because we were asked to work towards the back and get to the back phase so we can
bring
the operation
final from this phase,
you know, going
in this direction towards the front.
So we can't get to the back phase until we,
you know,
we complete through here.
Okay. And which phase is the back
>> considered? This is the back phase from from Station 5 to 65. That's the end of the project is at 565
at the top of the slope of the last hill.
And that all this grading
and that's where all the material is stored up there and now the topsoil and the remaining subsoil
material that's going to be spread
along this whole slope to finish and any
moguls that want
to get built
for
the animals
as suggested by Hank Brunner.
>> So we've started What might be built?
I'm sorry? What did you say? Any what that might be built for the animals? Moggles.
>> You know, small hills and
valleys for the animals
in the back here.
Which there there's no he said he's gonna direct us in person at the time of the field milling. I mean, he hasn't given us any detail of what that's gonna be, but
whatever,
you know, they suggest we will build.
>> Okay. And I just missed, I didn't pick up on your cursor right away when you were talking about back at the near the beginning of your remarks.
The section in the middle, what was your main comment about that right where your cursor is now? I didn't find it when you were first talking about that. Can you just quickly repeat what you said about that area of the
Yes.
>> This area here
is a
pile, a stockpile of graded sand
which is different than the bank run sand. Most of it's been removed.
The bank run has gravel in it and it gets sold as structural material. The bank run sand, it's used for another use and you know that's why it's all sifted.
Again, this has had a has about a thousand cubic yards in it as of last week. It's now got
about a third of that removed, it's around seven
to 800 yards that
are currently there now.
And I would say probably by
the end of a
couple of weeks, this will probably be gone and this area will be graded
and ready for restoration.
And we can restore this entire area,
and once this is gone we can restore up to
any area close to the
topsoil. We got to keep this open
because that's going be the topsoil that's going to
go on to the entire area. So we can restore most of the phase
and then have an operation just here only.
So all the operations will be in here
and all the restored areas will be back here as we proceed towards the front.
And that's
noted in the schedule I
will get to when you'd like to see it.
When
is that schedule? I have it in the Leanne
>> as soon as we get done talking about the drawing that's up here now.
>> Okay so it's part of tonight's presentation? Yes. Yep.
And then just another question for Mr. Bell and then one maybe for Jim or Jed.
You talked about a meeting coming up with Jim Halsey and Hank Gruner. Has that been scheduled?
>> No. As I say in the schedule,
as soon as this gets
to a
close to final grade,
as we noted in
the approval a couple years ago, we're going to have a meeting with Jim Hallisey, Hank Bruner,
and
I believe it's the chairman of Wetlands, Jim,
was it?
I'm not sure.
No, I believe the Wetlands Agent. Wetlands Agent, yes, I'm sorry. And we're
going to discuss
and conclude
the way
the town would like this thing finished off as far as you know grading, moguls, plantings and the like in the back phase.
>> Okay,
thank you. And then my question
for maybe Jim or Jed was just on the Town website where we were directed to, I think, by Jed's e mail to look at applications
that are submitted or pending. I didn't see this there, but I saw the other items that were on the agenda tonight. Is that just an oversight if someone were to start out by looking there? You know, like somebody from the public? Or is that just is this in a different category of applications that are Let me address that, Leigh Ann.
>> And maybe I goofed up.
I tried to send out
an email to all the Commission members and I may have missed you,
that
all of this information is posted under the archived
application.
Okay.
So if
I
didn't send that to you, I apologize.
can't remember going through, know, thing normally pops up recommended names to send stuff to.
Then maybe yours didn't pop up or something. I don't know. No. I I did see that. I did see it under it's all under the
>> archive section. Archived. Yep. And I did look at that, and I did see this
information from the past about this application. I just didn't see it under the
more current, I guess, applications.
>> Right. It was not there. It's only under the archive section.
Even the new stuff is under the archive section.
>> Okay. I see. Okay. Thank you both. That's And we and that can that be put in there, Jed? So But it probably can. I Not dated.
If
That's a good word, Scott.
>> I have a copy of the application you gave in.
We
>> have all the information. Jim,
if you could just have Amanda put it in the pending section.
Guess it could certainly be done.
>> Was everyone able to see all the photographs through like that.
>> Yes,
that we're viewing right now that should be put in
>> also, Jed. I think it is. I think that is in
the archive section down.
All the photos in this printer at the bottom of that section.
But
going back, I think Commissioner
Persson was
alluding to the fact that there are some things being done differently
than we thought they were going to be done,
such as all
the stumps. I was surprised when I saw the photo of all the tree stumps there because I just assumed all that stuff was cleared out of there early on. And now tonight, looking at this picture, I see
that it was put into the wetlands there.
Not the wetlands, but certainly the buffer area. Definitely the We buffer didn't think it was going to be.
>> Those were supposed to be removed. Yes. A long time ago, Chad. I was not happy with that at all.
>> So my question is,
if I go back to look at the regulation,
it says the permit renewal application.
The Commission shall not renew or extend any permit
unless the operator is able to show through the report of a registered engineer
that the excavation already completed conforms with the plan of operations approved.
And whether it's the tree stumps
I went over a look today
and I shared Scott's
perspective that there looks like there's a lot of stuff going out that really doesn't make much difference to me one way or another.
But what did surprise me
was that when I went back to look at
the special
requirements for the approval of the special permit,
and I did see this on one of the drawings in there somewhere, the excavation shall proceed sequentially one section at a time
commencing with Section zero proceeding to Section five. Excavation shall be
permitted to involve two sections at a time.
However, at no time shall a third section be disturbed until at least one prior section is fully restored,
stabilized, and approved by the CEO.
In no time shall more than two sections be open, and at no time shall sections three, four, five, or six be disturbed without prior authorization from the town.
The owners engineer shall adequately mark each section to the satisfaction of the town.
And then it you know there's another one in here the engineers to inspect the site and provide a report to the town at the completion of each phase.
And
so as I went over and looked today, you know, and I know we've got this huge excavator open working over on the
east side of the site there.
And I was looking for where the refueling takes place because it's all supposed to take place over by the gas station.
And maybe we're taking that over there every time we want to put fuel in it. I don't know.
But I was looking for a spill kit where there was a different piece of equipment over there staged. Nobody was using it. I don't know if that was the refueling section or not. But
my question is, you know, it does not appear
that
the owner,
the operator,
or anybody has been
discussing
where we stand and how we're doing
with the zoning agent or the commission the way
we expected it to have been done.
>> The
tree stump pile is within 20 feet of the vernal pools.
I mean,
that in itself is,
that there's you know, he said four tractor trailer loads of tree stumps, but right next, must be, you might as well say right next to the vernal pools.
>> They are protected by the silt fence and I
was not happy when I found those in our field walk. I had no idea those were there and I've been Those were supposed to be taken out a year ago.
>> That they were. You're right. But seems like this is, you know, we're coming up for renewal of the application.
And this is the first time we've, you know, had a serious look at how the project is going from an
oversight
piece, if you will. And that
bothers me a little bit. Now, I'm enthused
about
trying to get those deficiencies fixed.
But from what I could tell, there were no zones
that have been stabilized
and
replanted at this point. Is that correct?
>> That's correct. As
of late fall,
this was the only area
that was open besides
the detention pond.
You couldn't
see past the hill that was here. This was
just a grading operation and they were going back and forth in here.
This whole removal
happened probably since January.
But that's three different sections.
I
>> realize that. And that's specifically what we said we weren't going to do. Yeah.
>> I mean they should have stayed within this bounds here and just finished
this area,
and then
they could have restored
this area. I don't know why they put the tree stumps back there.
They had plenty of room to put them somewhere else if they could have put them over here.
If they had trouble getting rid of them,
they could have brought them
any place except there, that's the worst place they could have stored them.
>> Yeah, that's just, I don't see any oversight
or someone that,
somebody that's
involved
over there
that cares about the actual
application
and what was written as Jed stated.
None of it and I would say that
everything should be restored before we ran anybody another.
Far as I'm concerned it's
nobody followed any of the rules, mean that swale that was supposed to be in there within the original
plan,
it was never put there where it was supposed to be, that retention basin was supposed to be moved,
John Valenti ok'd it and you know
I
never got nobody
talked to me about not changing
the location of their retention
basins.
>> So I am interested in getting the project complete as soon as we can. But I am also more
interested
in getting the site
to where
if we're not going to do what we said in the plan,
to hear what the
and maybe that's what your schedule is, Chris, going forward. But I
share Scott's disappointment that
we find all these deficiencies
in your draft letter that you gave to us last
month
that
it just seemed like that was the first
time in two years that we've been out to this site to see what's actually going on.
And we see that a lot of things are happening that weren't in accordance with the plan that we spent an awful lot of time
trying to craft so that we did a good job on it. I would agree,
>> Mr. Chairman.
I
had been out here a couple of times since the plan was approved.
Again, nothing really happened
very much.
All the operation was over here after they completed the basin.
This was,
when we were out there a couple of weeks ago was the first time since
the fall,
all this had occurred in that short period of time.
And
I wasn't
aware of exactly the distances until I went out there and actually
put each station in so I could make this sketch,
and I was very upset with how
much
had been disturbed and also this area in the back.
My schedule reflects
basically
finishing this area and restoring it
before we do anything else,
because it's the first area that's supposed to get restored
as far as going from the back to the front.
You know, if we do any restoration in here,
it's already going to get disturbed as we, if we did this first,
it's all going to get disturbed if we go back and finish this.
There's not much material left here to finish it, probably the best way to go is restore this,
then restore this, restore this before we even touch this. This is supposed to be last.
My
schedule shows that we're going to be restoring all this before we move on to any area back up here,
because I recognize what has happened here and
I don't think they should be going anywhere near here
or removing any other material until we restore
orderly all the way through here. I agree. I'm not So again, going back to
>> our regulations
that say the Commission shall not renew or extend any permit
unless the operator is able to show through the report of registered engineer the excavation already completed
conforms with the plan of operations approved.
And so, I do not think
where we currently are, as much as I want to get
this thing done so we
can
seed and
remediate
the whole site,
our focus
for probably
the next month
has to be
making sure that we're in compliance.
And if we're not going to be in compliance with the plan that we all agreed to, you know, the Commission understands what
the plan is.
>> Right.
First and foremost,
they do anything, the stump pile should be removed and somebody should be down there from either the town or
Mr. Bell
to oversee that. I don't think a stump pile within 20 feet of a vernal pool
is
a very environmentally
sound
thing that should be going on. Yeah. Really soon. So,
>> will proceed to your schedule letter here in just a minute,
Chris, but when do you expect, I know you mentioned we were going to bring those stumps out
of the back
so that we got them out of the buffer zone to the wetlands anyhow,
even though you couldn't get them hauled off.
I would have expected that to have been done by the time we got together tonight. I'm surprised that that's already
>> done. It
was supposed to have been,
and I guess there's delays with the person that's supposed to be moving them.
In this schedule,
I have the stumps to be
removed within the next two weeks.
And
the idea after that is to get
the prep done
for the back part of
the project so we can have the meeting for restoration.
And the restoration really should
continue until
we get the whole site restored,
you know, before the extension is approved at this point,
or at least have it so there's no more than,
you know, one phase that
is under disturbance.
And we should be able
to restore most of this
before we get to those front sections.
I'm
told that they can do it as far as schedule goes, but so far that's not
being proven as far as
getting those stumps out. I'm very disappointed with that.
This
is the schedule that we're looking at
and
it's basically to get everything restored
before we get into the front.
I wasn't going to get anywhere near the front to the end of June, which is really basically after the next meeting.
In other words, all this stuff should be done
before the next meeting,
and that includes all the restoration.
>> In your letter
that you gave us at the last meeting,
you said we anticipate the stumps will be completely removed within three weeks,
which is a week ago, I think. I know.
The back phase will be graded and ready for the aforementioned restoration meeting a week after stump removal.
>> So They didn't make it, no. Okay.
I was told and I put some extra time in that and I thought it would be enough time but it didn't get done at all.
They just started moving those
I think it was Friday and today.
>> So from a zoning enforcement
point of view, Agent Halsey,
what's the correct way for us to proceed here?
And I'm thinking we
can cease and desist
gravel removal
tonight
until it's all fixed.
We can
say his permit doesn't expire until the end of June and it's got to be done at the next meeting
or
we won't
approve
the permit.
I'm looking for a suggestion on how you think the best way to proceed is. Well, Mr. Chairman, if I may,
>> if we're not allowed to take any material out and then we can't restore
the areas that have been disturbed,
I mean, if we
have this amount of time until
the next meeting,
know, at least we can get
the material that's in the way
to have the area ready to be restored.
And
I was told that, you know, spread the topsoil and do the
seeding is not going to take very long at all.
But if we get a cease and desist then we can't do anything.
>> Well, that's not true. If I may, for the record Mark Brantz, that's not correct Mr. Bell.
Well,
would you There could be
>> an order can be issued that no more materials to be removed from the site.
And the order can also state that the disturbed
areas in whatever phase number is appropriate
shall be restored immediately.
You said that restoration
can't occur
until the material is removed. Why is that? Why can't the materials only be spread, long seeded,
no more material coming out?
>> Well, I only say that it would be,
you're
absolutely right. I didn't, I shouldn't have said it that way. I meant to say it would be more advantageous for us to get the material out that's in the way of the restoration.
>> I mean, we'd have to bring So that it would be more advantageous
to Genovese
so that they get to sell more material,
but they're in violation of their permit. It sounds like they're in pretty considerable violation. It sounds like they're in violation in a number of respects. That motion for approval, by the way, I couldn't find that on the website. You see only the letter of approval. I don't see the motion. That motion sounds really familiar.
Does anyone remember who drafted that motion?
I think it was John Valeni who drafted it.
>> Okay.
Because I remember that motion pretty clearly.
Yeah, well, it's I think I may have worked with him on it. Why don't you send it to Mark? Yeah.
The
way it's expressed sounds
mighty
like
me. Pretty clear.
Yeah, there's 26
items.
Yeah, that's me.
>> This is ringing a bell with me, no pun intended,
but I think that your client Mr. Bell is
not fully appreciating the situation that he's in
And it is of course, it's really not even the Commission's call, it's the CEO's call. The CEO
may decide
to order not one more shovel full of material removed from this site
until
certain things
are done. Stumps and logs removed,
a certain phase restored,
if they want to stockpile the material, stockpile it, but you know, the time for saying
we need more time to get the material out of there,
that ship may have sailed
quite some time ago in fact,
and it may be that
the applicants are going to lose the use of material because of some sounds like some pretty substantial
violations of a very detailed
approval motion.
>> Am I missing something?
Attorney Branson, if I may say something that you remarked earlier,
this is not a matter of money, he's not trying to make money on this.
I mean, I'm seeing the prices he's getting from material, he's almost giving it away. He's trying to get the site down
to an elevation
that he can get,
make it more attractive
to sell. I mean, with
all this material on the site, he can't develop the site, okay, and it's No not a matter one's gonna buy it, no one's gonna It's buy not
a matter of money.
You're saying he wants to sell, it's not a matter of money.
If he could
move this material,
he's got to move it back to where it was in order to restore,
you know, the back area first, because if we don't restore the back area first and start moving towards the front the way it is now,
we're restoring the middle and then we have to drive over it in order to finish, you know, the remainder part.
It's not a matter of money, it's a matter of just amount of time to get rid of it.
I mean, he could
have gotten rid of it all
and done the phases properly,
I'm sure he would have tried to, but he's not, he's having trouble getting rid of the material.
>> And so he opened up the entire site,
all five phases at once, because he was having trouble getting rid of the material.
>> He was having
trouble
with different people on-site contracted to remove the material. He finds the person he has now
is the person that put the stumps back there, and that's the person I'm having the problem with. He's getting rid of the material, but he's moving
to areas he shouldn't be in. And we didn't know this until the time we came back
after the winter and saw how much material has been removed.
I
would like the time to just restore
what's there now, obviously take out the stumps, we've got to get that out immediately,
and to restore that back area,
and that shouldn't take that much time. If we restore the back area
and get the piles that are out in front of it,
those are all, those all should be gone within two weeks, and we should be able to get this thing restored by the end of June.
>> By that I would guarantee,
Chris Bell, that there's no permit to store those stumps 20 feet away from those vernal pools. No, there is not, I know that.
And so, and I know that there was trucks moving material in and out of there today,
I saw it,
so if I was the
owner of this property
and I knew I didn't have a permit to drop those stumps or loads of stumps next to the wetlands,
I certainly would be working on that prior to a
grain of sand going out of there.
>> I've been after the owner every day since the first day I saw those. Oh, you see our frustration. Frustration. I I do, do, I I do. Do.
And I've been after the owner every day to get those stumps out of there. So it's a wetland violation
also.
Yep.
>> Just for
starters.
Yes.
All the things that weren't done on this site, I mean, bulldozed swale is written
right on the print that we approved,
that hasn't been completed.
The movement
of the retention basins was on the print,
that we approved
all these things and now you want us to let them still truck this material out of
Doesn't seem fair to the town
to allow this to happen. So, it's
a wetlands violation, think the wetlands commission probably could give them a cease and desist also,
alongside of Planning and Zoning Commission.
>> Well,
at this point,
what would he be allowed to do from this point
until the next meeting?
He would, he's got to get this restored.
Well we didn't make this problem.
I know.
Yeah
>> I think, I think Mr. Bell you're asking, you're asking the question that you need to be answering for the Commission.
>> You're saying what should we do? They're asking you, they're asking you what should we Are you going to allow us to restore the site between now and the next meeting?
The
question is where material can be removed.
>> I want to get the stumps out of that back end of the lot.
And if you can't get them off the site,
move them up
front where
you were talking about.
That's what they're doing But I'm surprised that this meeting that you had back in mid April with
Agent Halsey,
Agent Wagner and Hank Gruner
weren't,
you know,
guess I was surprised that I heard no feedback
about
the wetlands violation concern.
But my thought is,
this
may be
Agent Halsey's
ball and not
ours as a commission,
is that
I would like to have
those stumps out of there
and
why it is that we didn't follow the plan
discussed
at the next meeting.
Because if you don't come in here
to convince the Commission that you are
following the plan at that point,
which we
had approved,
we
have no choice but to not approve the extension.
>> That's understood, sir. Okay, so moving forward, I think everyone agrees that Stumps have to get out of there as soon as possible, right?
Is that fair to say?
>> Joe Wagner probably should be paying a visit on there. It does sound like there's a wetlands violation.
It's too bad we're sort of beating up on the messenger here. I feel sorry for Mr. Bell.
But wetlands may need to act here. Their fines are a thousand dollars day
and
wetlands, it's a pretty clear wetlands violation right now,
so maybe a thousand dollars a day will get their
Right, there's certainly have to bring to bring suit on that, we may have to bring suit under zoning as well at $2.50 per day. So there's a total $12.50 per day. There's a breakdown in
>> between the
town and that site, it's very obvious.
There's
no talking,
but when we approve the application
to let them do that, now whoever owns that site has not read that application and the conditions
that were put in the
approval.
>> Yep, this is Leanne. I concur with everything that's been said
by the various parties since I asked my questions earlier.
Mr. Bell, it sounds like you're on the site infrequently.
Do you have anybody's name that you are able to give us? It doesn't sound like there's been anybody checking on the stump removal, checking on much of any of this, checking on phase one and phase two and, you know, all the things that that have been brought up. Is there anybody else's name that you want to bring to our attention?
>> Well, Bill Genovese is the owner of the site. He normally
works in,
in
New Britain, that is a main site,
but he does go to Andover,
you know, occasionally, usually only if there's a problem
with his business.
But I've been after him quite a bit about these stumps, you know, since the first day I saw them and I put them in the letter that they, you know, have to be removed since I was at the meeting.
I,
The person on-site that manages the site is a fellow called Pat, I'm sorry, I don't know his last name,
but
he's the one that took care of all the other problems that we have with the silt fence, he got that done in a day, and did a good job fixing those.
And if
I tell him there's a problem with with anything out there, he gets it done very quickly.
And he's the person that's the manager on on the site. He's there every day, Monday through Friday.
His name's Pat?
His name is Pat. Yes.
>> But you don't know his last name, and he works directly from a I'm sorry. I don't. He does work for
>> A Wright Auto out there. He run he runs the site.
So does he run Andover Auto Parts also?
>> A Wright Auto Parts. That's what he he's the manager of the site, he's he's on-site all the time.
So he does both? He's he's Oh, mean, yes. This project and he also works in auto parts full time. Yeah. I mean, they they see him when the truck driver comes in. They they wanna get loaded. He has
the loader driver go out there and load them up and and come back.
>> So as far as you know, he's he's supposed to be doing both jobs every day, including this project that we're concerned with. Yeah. I mean, I remember he wasn't doing much on the gravel pit for quite a while because nothing was happening there. Now
>> there's there's about like eight to 10
trucks do come per day, not every day, but that's what they're coming
on an average.
>> Do you know if this Pat fella has even cited
the documents with all these requirements on it, or is he just out there trying to move material?
>> He has a set of plans and I've told him of the requirements.
Again, like I said, when I first came out the site with Jim, was surprised at how much material had been moved.
There wasn't that much moved the last time I was out there in the fall. Not much has happened. A lot has happened in the last few months.
>> Okay, well I guess,
Agent Halsey, my thinking is that this is in
the short term, this is an issue for you and Agent Wagner
to get together with
Mr. Bell and figure out
how to
remediate the violations
that are currently in
place.
>> Marty,
kind
of things would you first say should be done? I mean I think that this is way past
the zoning
people.
I think that they haven't listened Jed
one bit right from the get go. I think Mark needs to come up with some kind of plan
first
and I hate to put you on the
spot Mark, but
it's not the zoning thing didn't work Jed, sorry.
Didn't work.
>> Here's my suggestion first of all by the way I did find a draft of that motion on my computer from 2019
dated May 30. That's why it sounds so familiar to me it sounded like something I drafted I did.
I don't know that's exactly the way it was adopted when I have, because I guess the approval was in June.
My latest draft was May 30. So at some point I would like to see the motion as it was actually approved. Or may have been changes from my system.
I do recall it though that the commission wall was very specific about what we expected to happen both on the plans and the motion.
That final motion should also be given to Mr. Bell he can give it to whoever is in charge of this thing.
But I think the very first thing is for Jim and Joe
to meet out there with Mr. Bell as soon as possible.
Decide what you think needs to happen first,
and then we should craft orders for that both zoning and wetlands orders
as to what
we expect to happen
As to whether more materials can be removed while this is pending,
I guess I have to defer to the experts on that.
We might want to bring the town engineer into this, I think that's going be desirable.
My instinct certainly is to say whether it's money or not that they can't remove another shovel full of material until other things are in order
and whether he's selling it or giving it away I really don't care.
This is obviously completely out of control completely out of compliance with the plan out of control of the design engineer who designed the plan
and
it's got to be stopped And I think the way to do that is we start with orders.
We start with orders
of what is to be happening when I know you have a Mr. Bell has a schedule.
Joe and Jim can review that and see if they find it acceptable.
If not, we can shorten it up, but I think there's got to be some really tight timelines here exactly,
but I say orders, orders as to what will happen when exactly what will happen and when it will happen.
If those, and by the way for excavation,
we do not have to allow ten days for a cease and desist order, it can take effect immediately upon receipt. That's an exception in the statute. You don't have to allow ten days for compliance, You can require immediate compliance for excavation violations
and we should.
That way the fines will begin to accrue.
The thousand a day and the $2.50 a day will begin to accrue from once those orders are issued.
Whether we collect them will depend on how
whether we take an action to collect them will depend on how cooperative
the owner applicant is.
But
we can collect attorney's fees under both zoning and wetlands.
We can shut it down as far as making it developable for future uses.
I wouldn't hold my breath on that.
Whether this will be approved for anything ever
sounds very questionable right now.
And so the
owner clearly is not paying attention.
He better start
and at $12.50 a day, I think he will.
That's the first thing is to is to get this into enforcement
mode.
Then the commission by but your June meeting then you see what's what reactions you've got if you've got none, we're good if it's continued a month from now, like what you're seeing right tonight, then we simply go to court. He goes straight to court on this
>> and bring an injunction and shut it down. Attorney Brantz I think if you stop him from taking material out you'll get his attention.
I think that's a 100% chance of that.
I think they'll be able to concentrate on restoring the site
if the material is stopped from leaving.
>> That would be my thought. He's the net then he knows who to sit.
If he violates
that, if he violates that, we may refer this to the state's attorney.
>> Don't think he'll I don't think he'll violate that.
I don't I don't believe he'll do that. I hope you're right. If
I may ask just one more item and also
Mark.
I'm sorry.
>> I heard someone start to speak. I think you were talking and you froze, your computer froze.
>> Working within 20 feet of a vernal pool to remove stumps
seems like
you need some approval from somewhere, you can't just have the guy go tell him that get his excavator in there and move the stumps. Mean it's two vernal pools that are back there, stumps are within 20 feet of it, you can't just have them go back.
I mean there's going to have to be a plan in place for that even. Correct. Just for starters,
>> as far as I can see. There is silt fence back there right now, it's in place. Yeah. I just want to let you know it's there sturdy, it's you know it's not like it's not there,
but there
was one item I wanted to talk to
Commissioner
Person about, please.
You mentioned about the
detention pond.
I know that's an important issue to you and it's an important issue to me.
I really feel confident that
we should keep the pond where it is as long as we have the water going towards it, which it does flow towards that direction.
And I would like to resolve that issue
with yourself. Know you have a lot of concern for that.
Thought that was
okay, the way it was. Chris, I'm
>> not saying it for myself, I'm saying it for the town of Andover.
Saying it because it would be great if we could finally get a project that went the way we're supposed to
and it's not,
it's not Chris. I agree.
This one was bad from the start
And Mark drew up the conditions of approval, 26 conditions,
and I
think that they didn't even, you couldn't even get them to put the erosion control in,
so.
>> They,
that's the third page
of the plans that they have on-site.
Yeah. So they do have them
and
>> And there's nobody here that wants that thing to be finished
more than me.
I would like to see it done and over with.
>> But tonight Chris, I don't want
to go over and belabor the schedule anymore. Think that
needs to be revised
with
Agent Halsey and Agent Wagner
to find out.
Don't know what the wetlands rules are for
getting those stumps out of there at this point, but that's why the meeting with you, Halsey and Wagner
tomorrow
is probably
a good place to start. Yeah, there's nothing
>> should happen though Jed until
somebody else reviews what's going on.
Shouldn't be some sort of restoration plan. There has to be a plan, nobody should be touching
three, four truckloads of
stumps next to Vernal Pools, they shouldn't be touching them.
Nobody should be under I doing
>> like to mention the owner told me just before the meeting,
when they started removing the stumps, he said he believes they started from the back
of the stump pile.
That's what he told me.
Whether that happened or not, I don't know because I'm not there.
He said he'd already taken the truck load out, tractor trailer truck load out.
So it may not be 20 feet from the wetland, the vernal pools anymore.
But
I'll have to see when I get out there.
>> Okay,
but I think,
it reasonable that tomorrow we get Agent Halsey, Agent Wagner
and
Engineer Bell over there to
look and craft out what the immediate actions are
and then
what the follow on actions are
at the next meeting we get briefed on the actions that you've taken and
>> we'll go from there. I can be there tomorrow. Jim just has to give me a time.
Why don't we ask to coordinate that with Wagner?
>> Well, I do know that
Joe has a meeting tomorrow night.
So presumably he'll be in town in the afternoon.
I'll email it tonight and see what I can set up, Chris.
Okay, call me anytime.
All right.
>> Me just mention one other thing. If Wetlands is meeting tomorrow night,
Joe may want to issue some order
tomorrow afternoon so the show cause hearing can be tomorrow night.
It can be continued. Of course, are but remember show cause hearings have to be within ten days of orders issued.
So, a a preliminary order might be appropriate
for Joe tomorrow afternoon.
Does
>> it matter if it's a special meeting? Is there any agenda issue? Yes,
>> there is.
It's a special meeting.
Special meeting. I can't do it then. Never mind. Okay.
Can't be added to the agenda now. It's too late. Yeah.
>> Okay,
I think that concludes the discussion
for this evening on the gravel pit.
Okay, thank you everyone.
>> Attorney Branch, that was the extra thing that I was hoping that you would be here to assist with. I appreciate you sticking around. Quite all right. I'm glad I stayed too. I do remember that one quite well. And I just I did find the motion for approval on my computer system. Just emailed it to you and Jim. It may not be the final one but that's why I remember it so well and
this definitely needs to be raining so glad to be
of help.
Thank
you.
>> Do you want me to stay further? I don't think there's anything else
>> that
we need your assistance with tonight.
Right. You don't get a question further out there. Thank you. All right, thank you. Take care all.
Thank you, Mark.
>> Okay.
Next
item on the agenda. And we're going to start moving fairly fast here. I normally like to be done by 09:30.
Proposed revision of the signed regs, that was on there as a placeholder just
for me to tell you that I've done nothing on that.
The
update the next item is the update on preparation of affordable housing plan
as required by the Connecticut General Statutes.
And I briefed
last time that I was getting together with Bill
Warner
to
come up with a plan.
Fortunately, maybe
we didn't get funding from the finance committee.
They wanted to talk to me.
And
I've been waffling with how to go with all the consternation
on affordable housing as of late.
It turns out that tomorrow morning there is a
online seminar from the small town councils
of Connecticut,
that's not the right name, but something like that on preparing
the affordable housing plans.
And so I'm looking to get a little bit of enlightenment
on that on
what should be our way ahead.
But I don't know
how many of you read the
the Hartford Courant.
Two weeks ago,
this was the front page on Sunday.
And it,
you know,
a flashpoint in the racial equity debate and it's
about a
house over in
I think it's Woodbridge
that they want to change into a four
apartment
dwelling,
I guess.
It's not the
planning and zoning rules don't support that and
they're in a lot of heat. So that was two weeks ago.
A week ago in
the
Sunday paper again,
there was an article,
The Tragedy of Segregation
at Woodbridge Echoes a Pattern of Silence Across Connecticut.
And so I looked at all that and I said, well, this is certainly
I don't want this to be Jed's plan. I want this to be something that this
has got to be the Andover plan. And
so I'm looking forward to seeing how the other small towns are dealing with this thing.
And so I've not moved the ball any further down
the line on that one either other than to know that that is a current hot issue.
And we do have a requirement to have a plan by the June
2022.
Item,
unless there's any questions on that one.
Next item is returning to in person planning and zoning commission meetings.
And there's things I like about meeting on Zoom
and there's things I like about meeting in person.
And I was just trying to
get a feel for
the commission
members' thoughts
given where we are and we're expecting
that on Wednesday of this week,
Connecticut takes significant steps towards being fully open
on
our thoughts about returning
to town hall for in person meetings.
Anybody got any thoughts one way or the other?
I
>> would prefer to be meeting in person.
I mean, it's nice not to have to leave your house,
but I feel like trying to
really have discussions
and really see the materials
and that kind of thing it's a lot better to be in person
so I would rather be in person okay
any other thoughts
>> this is Leanne yeah I
guess I have mixed feelings. I I agree that it would be nice to meet again in person. I
have mixed feelings for several reasons. I think
the I like these Zoom meetings. I'm comfortable with them, but I understand what Anne means. There's a different element when you can see each other and see the plans are being presented instead of trying to see them on a small screen.
I think this whole the whole time we've had this COVID pandemic things literally change every day. So now you have things like, as you said, a
lot of opening up going up on Wednesday
and then people
what age 16 or over can be vaccinated now and things like that. So
another one of my questions is I'm just wondering out loud if
we would
let's say we started next month meeting in person,
would we still have social distancing? Would we still wear masks?
Maybe that's part of your question to us now, Jed. And one thing that occurred to me tonight is if we because my desktop doesn't have
a camera or audio
and we're
But that's a
able
questions. That's
my contribution. Question. I My
>> think sense is that we would continue to social distance.
I don't
know the answer
to the mask question.
I think the current guidance is that
they are saying if you are fully vaccinated,
you don't have to wear a mask. If you are not fully vaccinated, you probably ought to wear a mask.
I'm thinking that with the social distancing
in
people who
for whatever reason may be at risk. I saw
a report watching
Meet the Press over the weekend, Chuck Todd asked
the head of the C. Well, what if you're immunocompromised
and vaccine? What should you do?
And she said, well, you should discuss that with your doctor.
And
I think
those people
and my wife is in that category. She
is going to be having to wear a mask for a while longer. We're still to the point where we've only got one third of the people fully vaccinated.
So we're not ready to say that we can go sit right next to each other and all that.
But we'll do what we have to make the attendees comfortable.
And if that's everybody wear a mask,
I'm okay with that. But I do like sitting on Zoom where you can see the facial expressions and that sort of thing. So I would hope that maybe we wouldn't have to, but
that's still a work in progress. First
cut is
do we think we should?
There's
a time for both. The summer months nice and warm. We can have ventilation there and all that.
Maybe it'd be nice to try
meeting in person. The
>> board of ed that my husband is on has been meeting in person for about four or five months now
in the school cafeteria
and they still do a zoom for the public
but they have been meeting in person each person at a table so they are over six feet apart and they have not had to use masks
I think one person who has not been vaccinated wears the mask
but the rest are able to just sit far enough apart
and they still have a big TV set up with the zoom so that the public can be there for zoom so the public isn't all there
when they have public comment and things like that. It's been working fine for them. Okay, yep. I think that's a good model. That sounds
>> sort of reasonable.
Okay, well first step is we have to open town hall. And when we cross that bridge,
maybe
I'll look at doing the next one
in person. I would like to do the public hearing for
the Pine Ridge Road where we can
the drawings up and see those and
all that kind of stuff.
I think the crowd that we get at our meetings is much smaller than they probably get at the Board of Ed.
We can probably
putting
some extra people in there. We've never had more than three or four extra people show up at a meeting and
we can fit that in there safely.
More to follow on that. But I am looking at
trying as long as the numbers all keep heading in the right direction to start meeting in person again.
>> Not having been to a meeting in person,
do you typically bring laptops
to the meeting
to work off of?
>> We
typically do not. Now that doesn't mean that you can't.
And one of the most significant issues
that I will have
is
I use a desktop computer
and
I don't have a laptop.
And so
I'm comfortable being able to pull stuff up on the screen here. I don't know
I would not have that ability to do that in town hall and I need a little assistance
to do that. And I think Mindy has always
done a pretty good job if I've fumbled the ball on getting that up and I'm sure she might be there as long as she was willing to go and meet in public.
>> Okay, yeah, I mean, just as long as it's an option, I just think it's really convenient to be able to use find keys and everything to
>> go through the document. Absolutely run laps around me going through my book. No doubt about that.
>> Jed, this is Leanne again. Yep, go ahead. It
almost sounds like we might want to go another month meeting on Zoom.
And I think you or someone mentioned
about the whole town hall itself being open or not. And I listened to the last Board of Selectmen's meeting.
And maybe if anybody else was on it, they can correct me if I'm wrong. But they had a discussion about it. And it seems to me that
under the Governor's current executive orders,
they ended up leaving it or I think Eric Anderson said that it could be left up to Jeff Maguire as the CEO or something,
as to whether or the town hall would be open.
I don't know. I don't even know what the if there were any conditions or if it's just if they're going to be open, open.
And if so, what date it was? That's my understanding of how it was left with them.
>> Maybe couldn't come up with it with an agreement. No.
>> Oh, that's I'm sorry, Scott. That's that's right. You're you were two hats here.
>> Right. We could we couldn't come up with an agreement. We just dropped it in Jeff's lap.
>> Okay. So it's basically up to Jeff McGuire to decide what's going on.
>> Okay, I will see what happens come Wednesday.
We've got five weeks between now and the next meeting.
I'll let everybody know in plenty of time.
If we hold off another month, not the end of the world,
that will work fine, too. But
I do think that it would be nice to meet in person
a little bit.
And then nobody can hide with the camera off.
I
can see you all.
Okay.
Somehow maybe I shifted into new business here.
Old business. I guess it's just
oh, yeah, okay. Now we are shifting into new business.
And it's got the application of Adam
somebody, 128 Wheeling Road. Is Adam still on the line?
Yep. I think he gave up. So I'm not going spend any time on that today.
I think it's very similar to the application we just talked about on Whale Road. And
we'll
start the clock on that. It does not require
a public hearing. So
we'll
>> talk about that at the next meeting.
Then the
next one
that had a lot of stuff coming in late is the application of Scott BB
241 Route 6 discussion of previously granted
special permit for kennel operation.
And I need to discuss that
in more detail with Jim so that I can have an understanding of where we've been and
what we need to do there.
Essentially, I think Scott Beebe has been running a,
well why don't you tell us your
nickels worth on that, Jim, just so Well, everybody
>> apparently he was issued a special permit
allowing for a kennel operation
on part of the Post Farm.
It involved
the construction of a facility off Of Timestarm Road. Apparently there was a lot of litigation
involved.
He never built the facility.
The special department did appear to
refer to two parcels of the Post Farm, which comprised most of the farm. And he's been operating on there
for about thirteen years, I believe.
And he ran into a situation where he needs a sign off, a certificate from the zoning official
on a state form
to allow him
continue to operate.
Question arose as to whether I could sign
that, whether that's
there is an
issue. He never did file the special permit that was provided,
but that could be done at any time. There's no real
there's no time frame for that. The question is as to whether his approval that was granted
would cover what he's currently doing. It's it's difficult
to ascertain that given what I can pull out of the file.
I just wanted to bring it to the commission for discussion.
>> I know a little bit about it, Jed. Okay, what do you know, Scott?
I know that it went to court.
Scott spent all the money that he had
for his kennel, approved him to build a
whole facility up on the Old State Road
and
you know in the end after he went to court he spent all the money that he had
on court fees he didn't then he didn't have the money to build
the facility and he won the court case because you know clearly says that you can build a kennel on
town of Andover.
Scott, you referred to the Old State Road, what road does that mean? Well, Hutchinson Road was called the Old State Road then it turned into Hudson Road.
Farm, I meant Hudson's right.
Okay,
>> well, yep. I
don't know.
It sounds like the commission needs to take some sort of action.
He didn't comply with what the special permit was that was granted
a bunch of years ago, 2011 or whatever it was. And
so he's continuing to operate this business out there.
We've got very specific
regulations.
I don't know if we had them then, but we got them now on
kennel operations.
And so
I think
we need to see something that shows that he's in compliance
with
our regulations now.
You know, it's another case where
we headed off to do something, didn't do what we said we were going to do, and
who knows where we're at. So I'll get with Jim, more to follow, but that's just the introduction of something else that we will get to deal with.
>> This
is Leanne again.
Jim, do you know what it is that he needed a sign off from you for the state that you didn't have enough information on?
>> Yeah. It's a certificate of zoning compliance. I think it's by the Department of,
I assume it's, I believe it's the Department of Agriculture. I think I posted it.
It's just so that
the state agency that oversees
kennels,
They just want to know that
kennel is in compliance with local regulations.
So it's something that the state does for a variety of
activities.
So occasionally
I'll float a certificate in front of me requiring
zoning
compliance.
And this happened to be one of them.
What happened is he apparently bought out a
partner in the business. So it triggered
a
new certificate.
You mean fairly recently?
I think so.
Yeah, it was not too long ago.
>> Okay.
And that's how this came up. I was wondering, I was gonna ask you or Jed before the meeting and I didn't how this came up in the first place.
Okay.
So what's the next step?
>> Next step is for Jim and I to
sort that out.
>> And Jim, did you say you had trouble finding the meeting minutes?
>> No,
just the information in the file. I can go back and get the minutes. I just haven't because yet.
>> Well, the minutes, you sent that to me just before this meeting, Jim, I thought.
There's very little information other than the fact that it was approved. Right.
I
couldn't find much information.
That's all I remember.
We're
trying to find out what was approved.
>> Yeah. So I'm not I'm not quite understanding.
If you don't have trouble finding the minutes,
it it sounds like it's a big problem
that something wasn't filed or several things weren't filed in the building office.
>> No. I know. The the what wasn't filed was filed in the in the clerk's office.
When a special permit is issued that what what
where?
>> In the in the clerk's office. The the notice that is supposed to be filed on the land records
wasn't filed. And that's that's on the on the applicant. There's no question about that. And he was apparently provided a copy and chose not to for whatever reason.
That that doesn't fall in the building department by any commission.
>> Okay. Well, I'm not I don't wanna say too much, but I'll say two quick things.
One,
my recollection
differs a little bit from Scott's. And two, this was a very
involved
application.
So anything that we can do
to go back and revisit it would be useful.
Very involved.
Okay.
I'm older than you, Leanne.
Yes, you are, slightly. Just slightly.
>> Okay.
So that's
the discussion on that.
Approval of minutes, I would like to put off until the next meeting. I did have several comments on there and it's just getting too late in the evening.
So,
item eight correspondence.
Jim, do we have anything in that category? No, I have none. Okay. Administrative reports?
>> Just that there's a tremendous amount of building
activity going on.
Trying to stay on top of it.
That's all I have. Okay.
>> And again, we
you were going to take a look at
the taco stand place down
by Parker Bridge Road or whatever it is? I
>> do have that on my things to do. Yes. Okay. I would what I wanna do is pull up the special permits that have been have been approved for
that property and
contact the owner and discuss how it can be cleaned up. I I just wanna know exactly what was approved. And I suspect it's going take some time and I'm
short, we have very limited staff in the building office currently.
>> Okay, I understand. Yep.
Under Commission discussion miscellaneous,
I
heard
via Jim from Eric, there was some
thought that we should use open space funds
to build a park.
I know very little
>> specifics on that. What Eric was looking for at this time is a consensus as to whether the Commission was comfortable providing some open space funds, meaning the dedicated open space funding for design purposes
for
a parking area at Parking.
Parking area at the trailhead
>> I thought this was a park like
merry-go-rounds
and
seesaws and that kind of stuff.
>> No, no. Mean, there could be a picnic table there or something of that nature, but very limited amenities.
And actually, I believe it may have come to the commission when at such time as
it was purchased. This land was purchased.
>> Well, we had a discussion there. My
thoughts is that I keep seeing Diane Greniers
looking for ideas to go out with these community
grants, this program that she's trying to give money away on.
And my thinking is, why wouldn't this be
right up that alley? Perfect,
perfect place for the usage of that money. Yeah, because we have not been contributing to the Open Space Fund. And I'm still
a little disappointed but not as disappointed as Scott that we didn't
purchase this piece of property down on Merritt Valley for the town with maybe open space funding. So I'd like to build the open space funding up and if there's a way to get
parking stuff paid for by this other grant,
obviously that's a little more work on somebody's part but
think that we should be taking advantage of that opportunity.
Eric
>> did plan on attending the meeting but he was I understand. Out of town for And I just wanted to approach that subject with everybody to know what request might be coming our way. I thought we did purchase land
on Merritt Valley Road. We purchased
>> the land
on
East Side. Yeah.
A year ago, we were looking at the purchase of the land right next
to the school property that
30 some acres or something was for sale over that way.
Is
that who that was, Scott?
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah, that one, that one, yeah. Okay, great. Clock property. Yep.
>> So I'm thinking we need to build
up the open space fund and go out and get some more open space.
Anybody
else have any comments or miscellaneous items to discuss here?
Hearing none, move right on to final public comment. I see nobody left for that.
So
I will
looking for a motion to adjourn.
Motion to adjourn.
>> Okay. Any second? Second. Leanne, second. Scott made the motion.
All in favor, aye.
Aye.
Any opposed?
Okay, well we made it before 10:00. Sorry to keep
everybody here so long but we did have a lot of business going on tonight.
It was important we got through as much of it as we did. Appreciate And everybody hanging in
>> we'll see everybody on June 5 over at Did you skip over the approval of the minutes for the last meeting?
>> I
did skip over that and I intend to because there are several things that I had comments on
and I don't know the answers to them necessarily.
And it was going to be a fairly lengthy discussion, I thought. And I want to get us out of here by 10:00.
Thank you.
>> Meetings adjourned. Thank you everybody for attending and we'll see you on June
or the sixth, whatever that Saturday is.
Good night everybody. Good night. Night. Good night.